<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Abstracts on DAB23</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/</link><description>Recent content in Abstracts on DAB23</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Keynote</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/richards/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/richards/</guid><description>Title &amp;amp; abstract to be confirmed.</description></item><item><title>Archaeological information system of the Czech Republic: towards open data and research</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/pajdla/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/pajdla/</guid><description>The Archaeological information system of the Czech Republic (AIS CR, https://www.aiscr.cz/) is a core infrastructure of Czech archaeology. It integrates digital services and resources aimed at various stakeholders, e. g. the general public, professional archaeologists, memory institutions, and researchers. AIS CR fundamental mission is to enable &amp;ldquo;Open Science Archaeology&amp;rdquo; by providing FAIR data documenting current and past archaeological fieldworks including excavations, surveys, metal detecting finds, etc. Currently, AIS CR publishes more than 150,000 records on fieldwork events and documents, including 25,000 aerial images, 75,000 excavation reports, and more.</description></item><item><title>Open science/open archaeology: a Latin American view</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/izeta_cattaneo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/izeta_cattaneo/</guid><description>Open science and open archaeology have been developing steadily on a global level. However, there are still regions in which development is incipient. Particularly in what was once called the third world and is geopolitically recognized as the global south. In particular, our experience in Latin America allows us to offer a general look at this interaction between open science and open archaeology. Also, relating it to the great activity that has existed for decades in Latin America to achieve greater openness towards the adoption of open science, as recently proposed by UNESCO.</description></item><item><title>Documenting the collaborative commitments that support data sharing within archaeological project collectives</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/batist/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/batist/</guid><description>Archaeological research is inherently collaborative, in that it involves many people coming together to examine a material assemblage of mutual interest by implementing a variety of tools and methods in tandem. Independent projects establish organizational structures and information systems to help coordinate labour and pool information derived thereof into a communal data stream, which can then be applied towards the production and publication of analytical findings. Albeit not necessarily egalitarian, and with different expectations set for people assigned different roles, archaeological projects thus constitue a form of commons, whereby participants contribute to and obtain value from a collective endeavour.</description></item><item><title>Keynote</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/morgan/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/morgan/</guid><description>Title &amp;amp; abstract to be confirmed.</description></item><item><title>Scale, resolution, and the demands of computational modelling: a 'divergence problem' in archaeology</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/makarewicz_kempf/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/makarewicz_kempf/</guid><description>Archaeology, the archaeological sciences, and paleoenvironmental sciences are now generating increasingly robust and large bodies of diverse data sets that span vast temporal and spatial scales. Consequently, archaeologists now enjoy large, thickly described data sets, usually generated as part of targeted efforts intended to address specific research questions that document ancient human behavioral dynamics at local or sub-regional scales. However, these diverse data are only rarely united under robust modelling frameworks, ones explicitly designed to interrogate the correlative power of hypothesized relationships between defined variables.</description></item><item><title>Wikidata as a knowledge base and research tool for open science in archaeology</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/schmidt_thiery/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/schmidt_thiery/</guid><description>Wikidata is an open knowledge base, which a growing number of volunteers and researchers use to add content to the Linked Open Data Cloud. Linked Open Data (LOD) aims at interlinking openly available datasets and thereby facilitating the combination and joint processing of existing data from various digital sources. Wikidata functions as the central storage for structured data of Wikimedia projects such as Wikipedia and Wikimedia Commons and does not only record statements, but also their sources, acting as a secondary database.</description></item><item><title>From trowel to AI: open source-supported reconstruction of a Bronze Age fortification</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/simeth_et_al/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/simeth_et_al/</guid><description>The presentation shows open source methods to investigate, analyze and reconstruct the Bronze Age fortification at Stätteberg near the Bavarian Danube. The entire workflow from digital prospection, documentation of the excavation, reconstruction of the wall, material quantities and labor calculations, to the creation of vivid reconstructions and atmospheric illustrations using 3D software and AI, will be presented.
It starts with digital prospection using freely available Lidar data, which can be accessed in Bavaria via the &amp;ldquo;Bayernatlas&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>Мapping of the archaeological reasoning process in 4D: form of publication or excavation of another kind?</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/talevski_et_al/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/talevski_et_al/</guid><description>The process of the reasoning behind the available archaeological data is a very important segment in archaeological research. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s about the decision-making process during the field activities, whether it&amp;rsquo;s about publishing the results. Here, the experience of the team behind the excavation is of exceptional importance, and of course, the selection of appropriate and adequately applied methods, techniques, and technology for answering the existing questions. All in case of problematic approach in solving particular problems about the past.</description></item><item><title>Keynote</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/opitz/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/opitz/</guid><description>Title &amp;amp; abstract to be confirmed.</description></item><item><title>Keynote</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/romanowska/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/romanowska/</guid><description>Title &amp;amp; abstract to be confirmed.</description></item><item><title>Modelling with open or restricted data? A case study from prehistoric Northern Europe</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/bilotti/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/bilotti/</guid><description>In this contribution I model population dynamics and past land-use using predictive modelling on some case studies from the South Western Baltic region during the Neolithic and the Bronze Age. Besides the archaeological questions, I will focus on methodology and data availability. By definition, a model is a simplification of the reality that aims to explain observed systems and to predict unknown ones. Therefore, we always need to find a balance between complexity and universality, which can be seen as a sort of mathematical inequality, similar to the well-known Heisenberg uncertainty principle, which asserts the limit in the accuracy of measurement of a particle position and momentum.</description></item><item><title>The Digital Atlas of Notched Bone Artefacts (DANBA): a collaborative open science database</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/hunger_borkowski/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/hunger_borkowski/</guid><description>The Digital Atlas of Notched Bone Artefacts (DANBA) collects data on notched bone artefacts on a global scale to implement data science methods in a cross-cultural approach for the functional analysis of notched bone artefacts.
Notched bone artefacts have a worldwide distribution and occur from the Paleolithic to the Modern period. Whereas, for specimens from the Americas the function as rhythmic idiophones is confirmed by historic and ethnographic sources, alternative propositions for notched bone artefacts from Africa, Europe and West Asia include, e.</description></item><item><title>CLIOdynamic ARCHaeology: computational approaches to critical pinch points in European Final Palaeolithic archaeology and climate change</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/riede_et_al/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/riede_et_al/</guid><description>Characterised by a series of dramatic climatic changes, the Last Glacial-Interglacial Transition (15,000-11,000 BP) was also witness to cultural transformations of Final Palaeolithic societies that are said to foreshadow the full development of regional entities during the subsequent Mesolithic. Research historical and source-critical analyses have, however, repeatedly questioned the validity of many of the cultural units used in this period; similarly, it is not clear to what degree social transmission dynamics drove the cultural changes observed in the archaeological record, or whether these reflect adaptations to changing environs.</description></item><item><title>The human niche space of Late Upper Paleolithic Europe and the effects of climate and population growth</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/yaworsky_et_al/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/yaworsky_et_al/</guid><description>Over the past decade, with the advent of affordable and powerful personal computers, a plethora of high resolution remotely sensed data, and significant advancements in data storage, archaeology has moved into a digital age, with many key insights gleamed from the use of these new technologies and big data. With this advancement many questions have arisen pertaining to making these analyses reproducible, how to make these data available for other researchers, and data standards.</description></item><item><title>Keynote</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/bogdani/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/bogdani/</guid><description>Title &amp;amp; abstract to be confirmed.</description></item><item><title>Open chronology: towards FAIR and transparent chronology building</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/levy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/levy/</guid><description>This paper discusses the opportunity and means to build archaeological chronologies in a FAIR and transparent way. Several current research projects, such as PeriodO (https://perio.do) and Chronontology (https://chronontology.dainst.org), aim at documenting chronologies according to FAIR principles. They offer linked gazetteers of chronological periods, covering a wide array of geographical and chronological horizons. Their fundamental work offer, for the first time, global databases of machine-readable archaeological chronologies. Yet, to the best of our knowledge, such projects archive final chronologies (i.</description></item><item><title>XRONOS: open chronometric data from archive to infrastructure</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/roe_hinz/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/roe_hinz/</guid><description>Chronometric data has been one of the principle domains in which open data and open science approaches have been applied over the last ten years. Comprehensive compilations of radiocarbon dates have become available for many parts of the world in the last decade and, as natural next step, there are now several initiatives to collate this data globally, including the retrieval tool c14bazAAR (Schmid et al. 2019), the IntChron exchange format (Bronk Ramsey et al.</description></item><item><title>*Mare Cyprium*: multimedia applications for Cypriot maritime cultural heritage</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/secci/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/secci/</guid><description>Funded by the Honor Frost Foundation (HFF), the Mare Cyprium Project is a digital archaeology public outreach exercise. It integrates data produced by the Maritime Archaeological Research Laboratory (MARELab), University of Cyprus (UCY) into a series of digital multimedia applications (DMAs). The main aim is to promote the value and complexity of Cypriot maritime cultural heritage. The project will focus on diverse case studies attempting to reach a diversified public. The case studies include artefacts, shipwrecks, harbours, and traditional boats.</description></item><item><title>Architectural study and restitution of the Greco-Roman temple of Sobek and Harwer in Kom Ombo (Upper Egypt)</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/terrier/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/terrier/</guid><description>At the heart of important economic issues, the exploitation and modern use of archaeological sites often take precedence over their study. The temple of Kom Ombo, located along the Nile cruises journey, is one of the essential stops for thousands of tourists. It is therefore directly concerned by the problems of wear and tear, maintenance and conservation of structures that often go beyond the framework defined by the Venice Charter.</description></item><item><title>Connecting the dots – linking coin finds</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/ackermann_et_al/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/ackermann_et_al/</guid><description>The Swiss Inventory of Coin Finds was founded in 1992 as a documentation centre that records and documents numismatic sources from Switzerland and the Principality of Liechtenstein. With no physical collection of its own, handling digital data was a requirement from the start. The physical aspects of antique coins—a handmade, mass-produced, and precisely datable object— are ideally suited to being described in a standard way. After an increasing interest in ancient numismatics during the Renaissance, the Austrian numismatist Joseph Eckhel (1737–1798) detailed for the first time the basic elements of coins like metals, denominations, legends, type descriptions, etc.</description></item><item><title>Digital glyptics: new approaches to the study of stamp-seals from the Southern Levant</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/m%C3%BCnger_levy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/m%C3%BCnger_levy/</guid><description>The paper presents ongoing research of the Swiss-Israeli project &amp;ldquo;Stamp-seals of the Southern Levant – A Multi-faceted Prism for Studying Entangled Histories in an Interdisciplinary Perspective&amp;rdquo;, funded by the Swiss National Science Foundation. In this presentation, we focus on aspects of data visualization and analysis, following a digital humanities approach.
The project&amp;rsquo;s database comprises ca. 12,000 items unearthed in controlled excavations both in Israel/Palestine and Jordan. It is based on Othmar Keel&amp;rsquo;s pioneering work, whose printed &amp;ldquo;Corpus of stamp-seal amulets&amp;rdquo; comprises ca.</description></item><item><title>Digital media for communicating archaeological research: text, Twine, VR</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/sampatakou/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/sampatakou/</guid><description>Archaeologists are keen to try digital media and cutting-edge technology to study the past or to present their research to the wider public. Digital archaeology is an established field of archaeology usually focused on using digital technology to study or communicate the past. Interactivity and immersion along with archaeological storytelling are often used to create digital heritage experiences, such as Virtual Reality (VR) installations, to communicate archaeological research to the public and to attract more visitors to the museums and cultural institutions.</description></item><item><title>Keynote</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/marwick/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/marwick/</guid><description>Title &amp;amp; abstract to be confirmed.</description></item><item><title>OsteoAR: An educational mobile augmented reality application for an archaeozoological bone atlas</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/damiano_g%C3%BCr%C3%A7%C4%B1nar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/damiano_g%C3%BCr%C3%A7%C4%B1nar/</guid><description>Extended reality (XR) technologies gained popularity in Archaeology over the years by enabling the visualization of complex 3D geometry in interactive environments. One of the advantages of these technologies is that they can make visual Archeological data widely accessible. However, adapting XR in the educational context of Archaeology requires further research. In this preliminary study, the potential of these technologies will be explored in the field of Archaeozoology. Archaeozoologists study faunal remains recovered from archaeological sites to analyze past animal-human relationships.</description></item><item><title>Poster presentation</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/batlle/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/batlle/</guid><description>The benefits of data opening for both science and society have been widely exposed. Data sharing not only helps making research more sustainable but also accelerates innovation, and Archaeology is not an exception. In fact, the openness of Archaeology in general and of archaeological research data has been seen not only as a beneficial practice but necessary, as a practically imperative solution to the already destructive nature of the archaeological research method, as well as an ethical obligation for a discipline that studies a public good such as heritage and uses mostly public funding.</description></item><item><title>Reproducibility with R applied to the study of Palaeolithic distribution sites</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/d%C3%ADaz-rodr%C3%ADguez/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/d%C3%ADaz-rodr%C3%ADguez/</guid><description>In recent years there has been an increase in archaeological studies based on Open Science. It is increasingly common for archaeologists to publish the code and data used in their academic work and this allows any researcher, with basic knowledge, to use this information, apply it to their own studies or adapt it to their problems. However, for the information used and generated from an archaeological investigation to be accessible to most researchers, it must have a series of basic criteria that make it understandable to any researcher.</description></item><item><title>Seeing what cannot be seen: theoretical considerations regarding virtual reconstructions and visualization of prehistoric archaeological sites</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/tzerpou_barcel%C3%B3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/abstracts/tzerpou_barcel%C3%B3/</guid><description>In the last decades, virtual reconstructions of historic buildings and archaeological sites have been frequently implemented both for research and dissemination purposes creating widely accessible and immersive content. However, certain concerns arise related to theoretical considerations as well as to practical hazards in the creation of models.
This poster will focus on the presentation and analysis of the theoretical considerations regarding virtual reconstructions and visualization of prehistoric archaeological sites. It will present existent critics of the use of virtual models, structure a theoretical framework for their implementation, and propose an alternative for the virtual models to be more dynamic and better designed for dissemination purposes (e.</description></item></channel></rss>