<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>News on DAB23</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/news/</link><description>Recent content in News on DAB23</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dab23.archaeological.science/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Streaming &amp; virtual participation</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/news/streaming/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/news/streaming/</guid><description>Digital Archaeology Bern begins tomorrow, 1 February 2023, at 8.00 CET.
We have an exciting programme of talks and posters over two days.
For those who will not be joining us in Bern, talks will be streamed online via Zoom:
https://unibe-ch.zoom.us/j/65088690725?pwd=SUtVVGgvRHRaWmpmWldPbHdpbmJtZz09 Meeting-ID: 650 8869 0725 Password: 794586 It will also be possible to ask questions of the speakers online. All are welcome to participate.</description></item><item><title>Preliminary programme available</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/news/preliminary_programme/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/news/preliminary_programme/</guid><description>The second colloquium in the Digital Archaeology Bern series will take place on 1–3 February 2023, on the topic of &amp;ldquo;advancing open research into the next decade&amp;rdquo;.
We are pleased to announce that following the call for papers we have a full two-day programme consisting of 6 keynote talks from invited speakers, plus an additional 13 oral presentations, and 8 poster presentations, organised into the following thematic sessions:
S1: Open Science in Archaeology: Impact &amp;amp; Significance S2: Archaeology, Open Science &amp;amp; the Digital Humanities S3: Practical Applications Plus a dedicated poster session on the first evening of the conference.</description></item><item><title>Registration open</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/news/registration_open/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/news/registration_open/</guid><description>Registration is now open for the second colloquium in the Digital Archaeology Bern series will take place on 1–3 February 2023, on the topic of &amp;ldquo;advancing open research into the next decade&amp;rdquo;. The registration deadline is 23 December 2022.
Click here to register.
Registration fees are as follows:
Presenting participants: 60 CHF Non-presenting participants: 100 CHF BA and MA students are exempt from the registration fee. Funds are also available to support participants&amp;rsquo; travel and accommodation expenses.</description></item><item><title>Call for Papers</title><link>https://dab23.archaeological.science/news/call_for_papers/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dab23.archaeological.science/news/call_for_papers/</guid><description>The second colloquium in the Digital Archaeology Bern series will take place on 1–3 February 2023, on the topic of &amp;ldquo;advancing open research into the next decade&amp;rdquo;.
The colloquium will consist of three main sessions dealing with the following topics:
The impact and significance of open science in archaeology to date The interaction between archaeology, open science and the digital humanities Practical applications and exemplars for open science in archaeological research in the next decade All three sessions will feature presentations from invited keynote speakers and from an open call for papers.</description></item></channel></rss>